Register of the Elizabeth Malozemoff (Elizaveta Andreevna Malozemova) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Elizabeth Malozemoff (Elizaveta Andreevna Malozemova) papers
1926-1971
2000C103
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Correspondence, biographical data, printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian literature, and to Russians in the United States.
Malozemoff, Elizabeth, b. 1881
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Elizabeth Malozemoff was born in St. Petersburg, Russia, on 26 July 1881. Emigrating to California after the Russian Revolution, she received a full education at the University of California at Berkeley, culminating with a Ph. D. in Russian literature in 1938.
She corresponded with a large number of émigré writers, including Aleksandr Otsup (Sergei Gornyi), Dmitrii Klenovskii, Rodion Berezov, Irina Saburova, and Aleksei Remizov. In addition to this collection, the researcher may also wish to consult Malozemoff's oral history interview, part of the Russian émigré project administered by the Regional Oral History Office of the University of California at Berkeley. Malozemoff's sons Andrew and Plato also achieved prominence: the first as a historian and the second as a mining engineer and chief executive of Newmont Mining Corporation. Elizabeth Malozemoff died in New York state in April 1974.
Chronology
1891 Born, St. Petersburg, Russia
1922 B. A., University of California, Berkeley
1929 M. A. University of California, Berkeley
1938 Ph.D., Russian literature, University of California, Berkeley
Scope and Content Note
The most significant materials in this collection are contained in the correspondence file, particularly the correspondence with émigré Russian writers such as Nina Fedorova (Riasanovsky) and Nikolai Narokov. Writings by and clippings about two prominent émigrés, Anna Mazurova and Sergei Gornyi, have been placed in the subject file under their names.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1930-1971 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Educational records, papers relating to E. A. Malozemoff's son, Plato, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1928-1968 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Subject File, 1926-1962 (Box 1)
  Clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, and writings, arranged alphabetically by heading
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1930-1971 (Box 1)
  - Educational records (Folder 1: 1)
  - Family file -- Plato Malozemoff (son). Birthday postcard, 1930, and clippings relating to his career as a mining executive (Folder 1: 2)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 3)
    Includes college notes and syllabi, 1946-1947, perhaps of Malozemoff's other son, Andrew
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1928-1968
  - General, 1928-1968 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 1: 5)
  - Arensburger, K., 1962 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Avtonomov, Nikolai Pavlovich, 1956-1961 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Berezov, Rodion, 1964 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Bunina, V., 1951 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Damanskaia, A., 1941 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Dolgopolov, Aleksandr, 1964 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Dudorova, N., n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - Gornyi, Sergei.
    General note
    See Otsup, Aleksandr
  - Grot, E., 1952 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Gulenko (Goulenko), V., 1965 (Folder 1: 14)
    Includes offprint of article
  - Ilyin, Olga, n.d. (Folder 1: 15)
  - Isaenko, Evgeniia Sergeevna, 1965 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Khomiakov (Homjakow), G., 1965 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Klenovskii (Klenowsky), Dmitrii, 1965-1968 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Kutyrina, Olga, 1965 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
  - Losskii, Nikolai Onufrievich, 1956-1957 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Mazurova, Aleksandra, 1934-1961 and undated (Folder 1: 21)
    See also SUBJECT FILE
  - Mort, Viktor Konstantinovich, 1964 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Narokov, Nikolai V., 1955-1967 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Nikolaeva, A., 1968 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Otsup, Aleksandr (pseud. Sergei Gornyi), 1926-1938 and undated (Folder 1: 25)
    Includes photographs of Gornyi and family members (?).
  - Poltoratskaia (Poltoratzky), Marianna A., 1962-1968 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Pomerantsev, Kirill, 1965-1966 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Presniakova, Elena, 1965 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Remizov, Aleksei Mikhailovich, 1952 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Riasanovsky (Fedorova), Nina, 1961-1968 and undated (Folder 1: 30)
  - Russian Center, San Francisco, 1944 and undated (Folder 1: 31)
  - Saburova, Irina, 1959-1960 and undated (Folder 1: 32)
  - Soboleva, Galina, 1966 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Taranik, M., 1964 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Tovstopiat, Ivan Danilovich, 1966 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Vuus (?), K., 1968 and undated (Folder 1: 36)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1926-1962
  Clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, writings and other matter
  - Gornyi, Sergei.
  - Mazurova, Aleksandra. (Folder 1: 37-38)
    Includes Mazurova's correspondence with an unidentified individual in the Soviet Union, 1930, as well as writings by Mazurova and by the unidentified individual
  - Otsup, Aleksandr (pseud. Sergei Gornyi). (Folder 1: 39)
    Includes clippings about and writings by him
  - Russian Americans. Mainly advertisements, programs and reviews of concerts, literary evenings, lectures, and other public events (Folder 1: 40)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 41)
    Clippings, largely relating to events in the Soviet Union